You may be wondering why do we need to find optimal policies
你可能会疑问 既然基于值的方法似乎效果很好
directly when value-based methods seem to work so well.
为何要直接查找最优策略
There are three arguments we'll consider, simplicity,
原因有三个方面
stochastic policies, and continuous action spaces.
简单性 随机性策略和连续动作空间
Remember that in value-based methods like Q-learning,
在 Q 学习等基于值的方法中
we invented this idea of a value function as
我们发明了值函数这一概念
an intermediate step towards finding the optimal policy.
作为查找最优策略的中间步骤
It helps us rephrase the problem in terms
它有助于我们将问题重新描述为
of something that is easier to understand and learn.
更易于理解和学习的形式
But if our ultimate goal is to find that optimal policy,
但是如果我们的最终目标是查找最优策略
do you really need this value function?
真的需要该值函数吗？
Can we directly estimate the optimal policy?
可以直接估算最优策略吗？
What would such a policy look like?
这样的策略看起来如何？
If we go with a deterministic approach,
如果我们采用确定性方法
then the policy simply needs to be a mapping or function from states to actions.
则该策略只需是从状态到动作的映射或函数
And in the stochastic case,
对于随机性方法
this would be the conditional probability of each action given a certain state.
则为在特定状态下每个动作的条件概率
We would then choose an action based on this probability distribution.
然后根据该概率分布选择一个动作
This is simpler in the sense that we are directly getting to the problem at hand,
这样更简单 因为我们直接处理手头上的问题
but it also avoids having to store a bunch of
并且可以避免处理大量额外的数据
additional data that may or may not always be useful.
这些数据并非始终有用
For example, large portions of the state space may have the same value.
例如 状态空间的很大部分可能具有相同的值
Formulating the policy in this manner allows us to make such generalizations where
以这种方式构建策略使我们能够在可能时进行此类泛化
possible and focus more on the complicated regions of the state space.
并更侧重于状态空间的更复杂区域
One of the main advantages of policy-based methods over
与基于值的方法相比 基于策略的方法具有的主要优势之一是
value-based methods is that they can learn true stochastic policies.
它们可以学习真正的随机性策略
This is like picking a random number from a special kind of machine.
这就像从一种特殊的机器中选择一个随机数字
One, where the chances of each number being
首先 每个数字被选择的概率
selected depends on some state variables that can be changed.
取决于可以更改的某些状态变量
In contrast, when we apply epsilon-greedy actions selection to a value function,
相反 当我们对值函数应用 Epsilon 贪婪动作选择法时
that does add some randomness, but it's a hack.
的确会增加一些随机性 但并不足够
Flip a coin, if it's heads follow a deterministic policy,
抛掷硬币 如果正面朝上 遵守确定性策略
hence pick an action at random.
因此随机选择一个动作
The underlying value function can still drive
底层的值函数依然会促使我们
us towards certain actions more than others.
选择特定的动作
Let's see how this can be problematic.
我们来看看其中存在的问题
Say you're learning to play rock-paper-scissors.
假设你要学习如何玩剪刀石头布
Scissors cut paper, paper covers rock,
剪刀可以剪开布 布可以包裹石头
and rock break scissors.
石头可以敲碎剪刀
Your opponent reveals their move at the same time as you.
对手同时伸出自己的手
So you can't really use that to decide what to pick.
因此你无法使用该信息来决定选择什么动作
In fact it turns out that the optimal policy
实际上 这里的最优策略是
here is to choose an action uniformly at random.
随机均匀地选择一个动作
Anything else, like a deterministic policy or even a stochastic policy,
任何其他策略 例如确定性策略
with some non-uniformity can be exploited by the opponent.
甚至有一定的不均匀性的随机性策略都会被对手利用
Another situation where a stochastic policy helps is when we have aliased states,
随机性策略有帮助的另一个情形是别名状态
that is, two or more states that we perceive to be identical but are actually different.
即我们认为相同的两个或多个状态实际上并不相同
In this sense, their environment is partially observable,
没错 从这一角度考虑 它们的环境部分可观察
but such situations can arise more often than you think.
但是此类情形出现的次数比你想象的要频繁
Consider this grid world for instance,
例如这个网格世界
which consists of smooth, white,
其中包含平滑的白色单元格
and rough gray cells,
和网状灰色单元格
and there is a banana in the bottom metal cell and a chili,
在底部中间单元格有一根香蕉
each in the bottom-left and right corners.
在左下角和右下角有一个辣椒
Obviously, agent George needs to find a reliable policy to get to
很明显 无论从哪个单元格开始 智能体 George 都需要找到一个可靠的策略
the banana and avoid landing on the chilies no matter what cell he starts in.
以便抵达香蕉单元格并避免进入辣椒单元格
But here's the catch,
实际情况是
all he can sense is whether the current cell is
它所知道的信息是当前单元格是否平滑
smooth or rough and whether it has a wall on each side.
两边是否有墙壁
Think of this as the only observations
假设这些是可以从环境中获取的
or features that are available from the environment.
唯一观察结果或特征
He can't sense anything about neighboring cells either.
它不能了解关于临近单元格的任何信息
When George is in the top middle cell,
当 George 位于顶部中间单元格时
he can sense it's smooth and only has a single wall to the north.
它知道该单元格很平滑并且只有北侧有一面墙
So he can reliably take a step downwards and reach the banana.
因此它可以向下移动并拿到香蕉
When he isn't either of the top left or right cells,
当它不在左上角或右上角的单元格中时
he can sense the sidewalls.
它知道两侧有墙壁
So he can recognize which of the two extreme cells he is in and
能够知道它处在哪两个极端单元格中
can learn to reliably step away from the chilies and toward the center.
并且能够学会可靠地避免遇到辣椒并进入中间单元格
The trouble is, when he's in one of the rough gray cells,
问题是 当它位于某个网状灰色单元格中时
he can't tell which one he's in,
无法判断位于哪个单元格中
all the features are identical.
所有特征都一样
If he's using a value function representation,
如果使用值函数表示法
then the value of these cells is equal,
那么这些单元格的值相等
since they both map to the same state and
因为它们都映射到相同的状态
the corresponding best action must also be identical.
相应的最佳动作肯定也一样
So, depending on his experiences,
因此 根据经验
George might learn to either go right or go left from both the cells,
George 可能学会从这两个单元格中向右或向左移动
resulting in an overall policy like this, which is fine.
导致整体策略变成这样 这也没关系
Except for this region,
但是这个区域存在问题
George will keep oscillating between these two cells and never get out.
George 将不断在这两个单元格之间来回移动 永远出不来
With a small epsilon-greedy policy,
借助很小的 Epsilon 贪婪策略
George might be able to come out by chance,
George 也许能够碰巧出来
but that's very inefficient and could take indefinitely long.
但是很不高效 可能会花费很长时间
And if he kept a high epsilon,
如果 ϵ 很大
that might result in bad actions in other states.
可能会导致其他状态的操作很糟糕
We can clearly see that the other value-based policy would not be ideal either.
可以清晰地看出其他基于值的策略也不太理想
The best he can do is to assign
它能采取的最佳做法是
equal probability to moving left or right from these aliased states.
以相同的概率从这些别名状态中向左或向右移动
He's much more likely to get out of the traps soon.
它更有可能很快离开该陷阱
A value-based approach tends to learn a deterministic or near deterministic policy,
基于值的方法倾向于学习确定性或近似确定性策略
whereas a policy-based approach in
而在这种情况下基于策略的方法
this situation can learn the desired stochastic policy.
可以学习期望的随机性策略
Our final reason for exploring policy-based methods
探索基于策略的方法的最后一个原因是
is that they are well-suited for continuous action spaces.
它们非常适合连续性动作空间
When we use a value-based method even with a function approximator,
当我们使用基于值的方法时 即使采用函数逼近器
our output consists of a value for each action.
输出也将由每个动作对应的值组成
Now, if the action space is discrete and there are a finite number of actions,
如果动作空间是离散的 有一组有限的动作
we can easily pick the action with the maximum value.
我们可以轻松地选择值最大的动作
But if the action space is continuous,
但是如果动作空间是连续的
then this makes operation turns into an optimization problem itself.
那么这个最大化运算变成了优化问题本身
It's like trying to find a global maximum of a continuous function which is non-trivial,
就像查找连续性函数的全局最大值 过程不轻松
especially if the function is not convex.
尤其是如果该函数非凸
A similar issue exists in higher dimensional action spaces,
更高维度的动作空间存在类似的问题
lots of possible actions to evaluate.
要评估的潜在动作非常多
It would be nice if we could map a given state to an action directly.
如果能将给定状态直接映射到动作 那么会比较理想
Even if the resulting policy is a bit more complex,
即使生成的策略有点复杂
it would significantly reduce the computation time needed to act,
这样可以显著缩短所需的计算时间
and that's something a policy-based method can enable.
这正是基于策略的方法可以达到的效果